<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://mikaelabrough.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://mikaelabrough.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-04-08T12:11:15+00:00</updated><id>https://mikaelabrough.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Mikaela Brough</title><subtitle>PhD Researcher in Information Security </subtitle><entry><title type="html">On the start of a new project in the Philippines…</title><link href="https://mikaelabrough.github.io/blog/2024/philippines_climate/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On the start of a new project in the Philippines…"/><published>2024-03-24T00:20:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-24T00:20:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mikaelabrough.github.io/blog/2024/philippines_climate</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mikaelabrough.github.io/blog/2024/philippines_climate/"><![CDATA[<p>Typically, in ethnographic research, we seek depth ‘in place’ – a long-term, situated understanding of a singular, geographically delimited place. As the discipline has evolved, this idea has had to change – the ‘field’ can be a lot of things these days.</p> <p>My dissertation aims to combine depth of place with multi-sitedness, meaning that I use ethnographic methods in several geographically dispersed locations. This is around a common effort - exploring information security in the context of climate activism (as part of a broader effort to potentially unsettle some core cryptographic foundations). Working this way is really at odds with pure anthropology, which seeks rich and complex explanations of a culture <em>only</em> in and of itself. Comparison is an analytically complicated tool in ethnography, and generalisation is almost always seen as a simplification.</p> <p>The pursuit of multi-sitedness with ‘sociotechnical’ intentions confronts me with a methodologically complicated landscape. In particular, pursuing multi-sitedness with climate activists (who are not part of the same transnational group) in the UK and the Philippines requires some thought. It is important though that I explore climate activist groups only (rather than comparing different types of activism), since as explained in a different blog post, climate activism generates unique security dynamics that are exclusive to the movement. Having a common foundation is important when combining sites.</p> <p>Before thinking about combining sites, there is a more immediate question - <strong>why the Philippines?</strong> I have been asked this question innumerable times. There really are a number of reasons why the Philippines is an important space to explore climate activism and security (both informational and beyond). I have been pursuing my thesis work here, and am currently in the first phase of the project - remote interviews.</p> <p>I have been interviewing activists remotely for a few weeks now. I plan to go to Cebu City (and the surrounding area) for a month this summer to do some face-to-face interviews. I also plan to return for several months next year. In preparation for these visits, the remote interviews I have conducted have allowed me to understand some of the high-level security concerns of grassroots groups in the Philippines.</p> <p>In conducting remote interviews as part of an initial phase of this project, I have asked myself three key questions:</p> <blockquote> <ol> <li>What is the landscape of advocacy and information security in this context?</li> <li>How will this site interact conceptually with existing work I have done on climate activism in the UK?</li> <li>What sorts of things do groups and individuals feel would be most useful for me to work with them on?</li> </ol> </blockquote> <p>I will now briefly summarise some contextual notes on what the Philippines offers in terms of understanding digital security/social movements, as described by interviewees (with some brief sentiments in the headers) –</p> <h4 id="we-try-joining-together-but-it-is-hard">“We try joining together but it is hard.”</h4> <p>There is no single big climate activist group in the Philippines; instead, there is a diverse range of medium and small groups that often work together. Numerous coalitions facilitate this collaboration, with some activists belonging to 5 or even 10 groups/coalitions. It is hard to speak about actvism ‘in the Philippines’, since the country is incredibly diverse and features stark urban/rural divides. In terms of environmental conerns, different provinces, regions, and collections of islands are concerned with radically different things.</p> <p>Why are there not one or two big groups (like we see in the UK)? According to one participant, there is an interest in uniting the landscape to have a stronger voice, but groups often lack resources and similar priorities. Issues of scale also come to the fore, with some groups preferring local struggles and others taking on transnational (regional or global) issues. Local forms of activism in the Philippines are just that, local struggles over land. More globalised or transnational groups take on broader, more global issues. Therefore, with a variety of smaller groups working together, there is no one way to ‘do information security’, leading to ad hoc security practices that do not always map onto each other. As someone interested in networks, the complexity of this network, particularly in terms of scale, is fascinating.</p> <p>In addition, while many groups meet in-person when activists live close by, a significant amount of organising is done online. This is exacerbated by the fact that some groups work regionally or nationally, spanning many different islands. One participant explained that the Philippines is a “country of digital citizens.” This is an important foundation for working on digital security strategy.</p> <h4 id="everything-is-about-land">“Everything is about land.”</h4> <p>When we think about activism, the first thing that comes to mind for many people is protesting. It is really the case everywhere that we see activism as much more than just protesting. People I have talked to so far in the Philippines have emphasised this - that there are many forms of ‘activism beyond the streets’. Different methods of collective action require different practices of information security, and so for people involved in different things, their ideas of security may combine or conflict.</p> <p>One participant defined climate activism in the Philippines in terms of three broad categories. The first is “activists who take to the streets”. The second is “activists who are more artistic or express themselves at the political level”. And then there are the land defenders, who are “different from the other types” because they are involved in specific anti-extractivist campaigns. There are five types of land defenders in the Philippines, roughly indigenous peoples, farmers/agricultural workers, activists, lawyers/judges, and conservation officers, meaning that many people doing this work would not consider themselves activists <em>per se</em>, as they are essentially trying to protect their livelihoods, but face intense threats related to the broader movement, meaning that ideas of collective security are relevant here, but can split significantly as groups have different essential goals in terms of their advocacy.</p> <p>Other forms of activism (e.g. mass mobilisations, small-scale protests, political activism, creative activism) also take on a similar ethos that climate activism is not just ‘for the climate’ but also defends livelihoods, workers and the connected lives of people and land. With different understandings of what constitutes climate activism and what needs to be protected, security manifests itself in very different ways.</p> <h4 id="security-involves-everybody">“Security involves everybody.”</h4> <p>Despite which types of activism they took part in most, interviewees told me that about the generalised fears associated with activism, meaning that security is relevant for all activists, despite their methods. I have been told that land defending is largely perceived by the public and government as a radical communist activity, making it the most dangerous form of activism in terms of arrest and death (given that there is an armed wing of the communist party in the Philippines that you can be mistakenly affilated with). Therefore, being a land defender carries a risk of being ‘red-tagged’, a process that Ferdinand Marcos introduced during periods of martial law several decades ago. To be red-tagged is to be added to a government database, and then arrested / killed extrajudicially. Therefore, the stakes are high.</p> <p>Some more context for generalised fears is the <strong>Anti-Terror Law of 2020</strong>, which was a culmination of many years of tightening legislation surrounding extremism. The 18th Congress passed the ATL in 2020 under Rodrigo Duterte, who expanded the definition of what it means to be an extremist. While Duterte is no longer in power, one participant told me that the structures that he introduced, and the cultural impact, endures. The law was petitioned 37 times, making it the most assailed piece of legislation in Philippines history. Duterte specified in the definition in response that “advocacy, protest, dissent, stoppage of work, industrial or mass action, and other similar exercises of civil and political rights” shall not be considered as terrorist acts only if they do not present a risk to public safety. Therefore, protest is not illegal (it is a constitutional right, which is important for information secuirty, as some legal protective mechanisms should exist for parties to strategise with) - but the reality is that certain forms of activism are thought of as terrorism under this new definition. At least 1734 killings of environmental and land defenders took place in a total of 53 countries between 2002 and 2018, most of them occurring in Brazil, the Philippines, Colombia, Honduras, Mexico and Peru (with 77% of land defender killings occurring in these 6 countries).</p> <p>With the ATL as the context, all other forms of protest and advocacy are also dangerous but are not considered to be extremist from a legal standpoint. The risks that protesting (both mass mobilisation and smaller scale stuff) carries are related to violent dispersion and “letting the police know that you exist”. Protesting without a permit is grounds for arrest, and involvement in nonviolent direct action (NVDA) can also lead to arrest. Participants explained that being arrested is undesirable, given that being seen as involved in illegal activity could potentially undermine the entire movement. While one might assume that people who take part in ‘less radical’ forms of activism act in less secure ways, this does not seem as true in the Philippines. All activists, regardless of methods used, fear their safety - meaning that “security involves everybody”, regardless of methods.</p> <h4 id="it-matters">“It matters.”</h4> <p>On a broader note, the Philippines is one of the most vulnerable countries in the world to the effects of climate change, despite contributing little. Therefore, this advocacy does not exist in a bubble, it does not exist in the abstract. It is felt, and is unlikely to go away despite legislative changes and threat. On a fundamental level, security here is more than just information security or operational security, there is insecurity in terms of life, livelihood, and the future.</p> <p>There is a lot that I want to write here but I fear it will get too long. Moving forward, I am continuing to interview organisers and campaigners remotely (while also continuing with my UK-based work concurrently), and then in July I will be in Cebu City (and beyond). I am really looking forward to it all.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Thesis"/><category term="Philippines"/><category term="Climate"/><category term="Activism"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Some notes on context, pursuing multi-sitedness, and remote interviews.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why study the UK climate movement from a digital security perspective?</title><link href="https://mikaelabrough.github.io/blog/2024/uk_climate/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why study the UK climate movement from a digital security perspective?"/><published>2024-03-08T00:20:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-08T00:20:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mikaelabrough.github.io/blog/2024/uk_climate</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mikaelabrough.github.io/blog/2024/uk_climate/"><![CDATA[<p>Being a part of the <a href="https://royalholloway.ac.uk/research-and-teaching/departments-and-schools/information-security/studying-here/centre-for-doctoral-training-in-cyber-security-for-the-everyday/current-cdt-researchers/">EPSRC Centre for Doctoral Training (CDT) in Cyber Security for the Everyday</a>, a conventional 3-year PhD becomes a 4-year PhD. This is because the first year of the CDT is spent in various cybersecurity modules, culminating in a ‘summer project’ that transitions from this taught year to pure research. The summer project was described to me as a sort of ‘thesis pilot’.</p> <p>Going into my PhD, I had a strong sense of the types of questions I wanted to explore, but not necessarily where I would do my fieldwork. Looking around to my former classmates from my MSc in Social Anthropology, I see people scattered all over the world in different sites. Despite the anthropological tendency to go <em>elsewhere</em>, I had the realisation that where I live in the UK is actually the best spot for a pilot, and in particular, the UK climate movement is the best subject.</p> <p>Having lived in the UK (mostly in London) for about five years, it feels like at any given time, people are protesting. When you walk around, you will come upon protests for the climate, systems change causes, various non-UK related causes, far right causes, anti-government, etc. (recently you will come upon many protests calling for ceasefire in Gaza, although this development fell after my pilot ended). Protests look and feel different in different areas – London is not Cornwall, just as Cornwall is not Leeds, and Leeds is not Glasgow.</p> <p>Londoners do have this kind of thing about them though. When one Londoner participant was asking my opinion on the climate activism scene in Canada, I described experiences in Montreal – where I spent my undergrad years. They replied something along the lines of <em>“But what can you confront in Montreal? Here, there are all the headquarters of the biggest banks. There is the national government. How do protests in Montreal turn violent? It doesn’t seem like there would be any major people or institutions to confront.”</em> I reminded him that Montreal is French Canada and that seemed to sufficiently answer his question about how our protests can become violent. In all though, protest in the UK both in London and in other parts of the country is distinct from the rest of the world, and in particular, environmental activism has a rich and storied history regarding civil disobedience.</p> <p>When interviewing an activist who has worked in both the USA and the UK, they kept emphasising that despite what makes the news in the USA, the American public perceives climate protest completely differently than the UK. This participant thought that this was to do with the civil rights movement in the US, where the public does not always get what protesters are being disruptive about, but they always passively support your right to do so. I was surprised by this opinion, given the violent clashes we watch on the news from the USA. This participant said though that in general, the UK likes direct action and civil disobedience more than protesters in the USA, and that this could be why the public is more hostile to protest in the UK (in their opinion).</p> <p>I mean, I have had endless conversations with people in pubs about protests, since as soon as someone asks what you do and you say the word protest, you hear all their thoughts on climate protesters in the capital. And in 2023, everybody had an opinion. Just Stop Oil made the news what felt like everyday and the government, feeling the public discontent with traffic disruption, passed the Public Order Bill Amendments in 2023. JSO leads to mixed opinions and was seeming to become an easy way to garner conservative support – after all, it is easier to blame JSO than talk about the more complicated grievances that people have.</p> <h4 id="pcsc-act-2022-and-the-public-order-bill-amendments-2023">PCSC Act (2022) and the Public Order Bill Amendments (2023)</h4> <p>Realising that this was a hot-button issue - there have been numerous legislative changes to the protest landscape in the past two years. The introduction of the Police, Crime, Sentencing, and Courts (PCSC) Act in 2022 resulted in five key amendments to sections 12 and 14 of the Public Order Act 1986. These changes allowed the police to impose any type of condition on a procession or assembly (any gathering of two or more people) that could be considered to be disruptive in any way (including noise, without specifying a level). Building on Part 3 of the PCSC Act amendments, the Public Order Bill amendments aimed to further strengthen police powers to deal with protests. The Bill introduced new offences, including locking on and ‘going equipped’ for lock-on protests. Locking on is the act of attaching oneself to a person, object or land for the purpose of causing disruption. Carrying a device potentially intended for lock-on purposes is defined as ‘going equipped’, with the maximum penalty now an unlimited fine. The revisions to the Public Order Act also introduced new offences relating to obstructing traffic, delaying infrastructure and tunnelling - with prison sentences ranging from 6 months to 3 years. In addition, police stop and search powers have been extended to include the identification of locking devices, and both suspicion-based and suspicionless searches. Individuals involved in protests can now also be subject to a Serious Disruption Prevention Order (SDPO) from the courts, which imposes restrictions or conditions on their activities - including their use of the internet, communication with certain people, access to certain locations and the right to protest in the UK.</p> <h4 id="with-and-against-the-state">With and Against the State</h4> <p>In this moment of tightening legislation and public discontent, climate activism was on everyone’s lips. Even if you weren’t in a civil disobedience group, all groups were being lumped together - making all activities dangerous for activists who don’t want to go to jail. Despite what the news says, not all climate activism involves protest, in fact most of it does not. The stated aims of most climate groups in the UK are in line with those of the UK government, which has signed up to the Paris Agreement and is aiming for net-zero emissions. Many groups are working within and alongside UK government departments to achieve these goals. As Hasler et al. (2020) put it, the dynamic can be characterised as ‘in and against the state’, with some activists working within the state and others being persecuted by it. This seems to create security dynamics that are multiple and complex in the sense that cooperation between groups can become complicated in terms of who is considered an adversary and the relevance of security within these models.</p> <h4 id="the-necessity-to-be-open">The Necessity to be Open</h4> <p>In climate activism, there is a constant need to be open to new members - creating security dynamics that are sometimes tense and conflicting. In some other types of social movements, which are exclusionary (in that you have to have a certain identity or social position to be involved), security is less of an issue because new members are expected to look, act and belong to certain social groups. For example, one participant told me that he sometimes joins far-right groups so that he can understand if they are a threat to the left-wing groups he has been in. He said he was able to do this because he ‘looks like the type of guy who would be in those groups’. That made sense to me - The Proud Boys are all men, for obvious reasons. In other words, many social movements tend to rely on some idea of what a ‘typical member’ is - but this is worrying in the climate movement. In the climate movement, having expectations of how members should look and act is incompatible with the movement’s stated goal of being open and accessible to everyone - because climate change affects everyone. People who are ‘more secure’ tend to bemoan people who are ‘less secure’, and conversely, the ‘less secure’ accuse the ‘more secure’ of being exclusionary. Thus, the need to be nonchalant about vetting new people clashes with the security practices that some groups seek to implement to mitigate the risk of police infiltration. In this conflict of priorities, climate activism represents a unique security space.</p> <h3 id="research-questions">Research Questions</h3> <p>With hundreds of groups operating in the UK and a rich history of environmental protest, I wanted to know how the movement’s sense of security (both digital and not) reacted to the changing political and cultural climate, and how internal dynamics reflected the dominance and assumed disruptiveness of protest as modelled by groups like JSO. Climate activists in the UK have differing opinions on the role of technology in the movement and how much they want to rely on it, and thus their perceptions of digital security and the danger that online surveillance presents in terms of infiltration and suppression (a real issue I was surprised by, there are many cases of undercover police in climate groups in the UK, in some cases having romantic relationships and children with activists while undercover) reflects these uneven perspectives. I always try and keep my research questions simple:</p> <blockquote> <ol> <li>How is digital security practised and perceived within the UK climate movement?</li> <li>What are the relational social dynamics that shape activists’ collective and personal sense of security?</li> </ol> </blockquote> <p>I was not just interested in people telling me about the things they did to feel more digitally secure, but I really wanted to know the broader context from which these practices emerged. So this project involved different forms of data collection within that broad framework.</p> <h3 id="methods">Methods</h3> <p><strong>Semi-structured interviews</strong> I interviewed 15 climate activists in the UK, either online or face-to-face. These interviews varied widely in length, with some lasting 30 minutes and others lasting hours.</p> <p><strong>Unstructured interviewing</strong> I interviewed 19 climate campaigners in an unstructured way, meaning that they completely controlled the conversation without me following a specific agenda of questions. These interviews often took place at events I was attending or immediately afterwards. I adopted this method because many people think that they need to have technical knowledge of digital security or computer science to be interviewed for a project that deals with these esoteric topics. Giving people this option, essentially a chat with a consent process, allowed people to just talk about the movement and their understanding of security without the pressure that technology as a subject can put on people.</p> <p><strong>Participant observation</strong> In other words, doing things with the people I was interviewing. I went to protests, meetings, trainings, workshops, a camp, and ran my own workshop at one point - the total amount of time was roughly 150 hours. I think that without doing these things my project findings would feel lost - participant observation is the anchor from which interview statements find their meaning.</p> <p>The findings from this study are forthcoming. And my engagement with the UK climate movement is ongoing, both from a personal standpoint and from a research standpoint. I am forging forward in this context, while expanding to other fieldsites – notably in the Philippines. I will make a seperate post about the reasons for combining these sites in the same thesis - there is too much to say.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Articles"/><category term="Thesis"/><category term="UK"/><category term="Climate"/><category term="Activism"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An introduction to my 2023 thesis pilot project]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Navigating the high/low risk binary - a theoretical article</title><link href="https://mikaelabrough.github.io/blog/2024/synthesis/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Navigating the high/low risk binary - a theoretical article"/><published>2024-03-05T00:20:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-05T00:20:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mikaelabrough.github.io/blog/2024/synthesis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mikaelabrough.github.io/blog/2024/synthesis/"><![CDATA[<p>Last year I wrote a couple of thousand words about the different ways in which existing work looks at how risk influences perceptions of secure messaging. This literature is quite diverse and challenging to synthesise, spanning HCI, technical security, cryptography, critical security, Science and Technology Studies (STS), and surveillance studies. I presented these words at a 2023 STS confernence organised by <a href="http://www.stsitalia.org/?lang=en">STS Italia</a> in Bologna. A couple critiques from the audience stood out:</p> <ol> <li>What about this existing data speaks to the self-perception of people in so-called risky social and political contexts?</li> <li>How are self-perceptions represented, and can they even be represented through boiler-plate qual and quant methodologies?</li> <li>Could these be scientific projections of what <em>we</em> assume about other people’s levels of risk?</li> </ol> <p>In reality, the questions were a lot more sophisticated than this but I admit I do not speak STS well.</p> <p>For some clarity, the literature on risk and secure messaging tends to divide people into high and low risk designations (particularly in security studies, HCI, and sociotechnical work). Low risk refers to people who are not going to be directly harmed by their information security practices - what people tend to think of as the ‘everyday person’. High risk people are thought to be the opposite - typical examples include: journalists, activists (my area and hence the motivation for the review), politicians, terrorists. What my work initially did was to review the results of studies that looked at high and low risk groups. Now I have rewritten the paper to look at some of the assumptions baked into this binary, some of the relational aspects of risk, and some thoughts on everyday security.</p> <p>This is the most recent abstract of the article -</p> <blockquote> <p><em>Information security research tends to divide people into high-risk and low-risk categories based on their perceived vulnerability to harm from digital practices. High-risk individuals, including activists and journalists, are thought to face immediate dangers such as targeted surveillance or physical harm. In contrast, low-risk individuals are assumed to engage in routine digital activities without significant threats to their security. This article critiques this binary classification within information security scholarship by exploring the conceptual and empirical instabilities inherent in this framework. Drawing on ideas from the interpretative social sciences, the article offers a disciplinary critique in three ways, 1) by bringing attention to relational aspects of risk; 2) by examining the normative underpinnings of this binary; 3) by discussing ideas of the everyday. I consider which aspects of risk this binary renders invisible and explore alternative ways of thinking about information security.</em></p> </blockquote> <p>While this article started out as a literature review, the current form is more of a critical review. I will be presenting this paper as a work in progress at <a href="https://www.ucl.ac.uk/institute-of-advanced-studies/news/2024/jan/cfp-looking-everyday-security-cross-disciplinary-workshop">Looking for Everyday Security: A Cross-Disciplinary Workshop</a>. The things I explore in this paper are as follows:</p> <p><strong>Relational Risk</strong> We do not have to look hard to see how the edges of high and low risk categories blur under scrutiny. When we say that some group constitutes a high-risk population, we imply a degree of naturalisation and boundedness. We frame this group were a discrete entity with some inherent characteristic inextricably linked to threat. Rather than a universal experience though, ideas of risk are created and maintained by a particular time and place. We can find numerous examples of how risk is linked to context, social relations, and subjective opinions.</p> <p><strong>What do labels do?</strong> Labelling across unrelated cases is an attempt to manage an unwieldy social reality. Since the results of studies depend on the specific group being studied, which is situated in a particular social context, this can create a sense of disarray for researchers trying to paint a single narrative. Trying to bring these perspectives together is trying to create one answer to a plural question. When technologists ask themselves ‘how do we design for at-risk people?’, this implies that there is a singular at-risk group where this is simply not the case. By labelling disparate case studies in one way (high-risk), we create and perpetuate the idea that there is one best way to incorporate this information into current design directions.</p> <p><strong>Everyday Security</strong> For many people, the things they do to create a sense of security in their everyday lives are just that, everyday. They can become taken for granted as people strive for an existence free from fear. There- fore, participants’ conceptions of risk may not follow a template of what researchers expect to hear about – instead of hearing about threats, harms and mitigations, they may hear about participants’ daily frustrations and everyday fears. By taking these everyday frustrations as a serious source of data, we can move away from ascriptive binaries and towards everyday security, studied in context.</p> <p>I will link to the article as soon once I know that I can. In other boring literature review news, I am currently embarking on the big one for my thesis…</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Articles"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A summary of some ongoing work]]></summary></entry></feed>